hello and welcome this is active
inference live stream 58.1 on November
7th
2024 Welcome to The actm Institute we're
a participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at links here this is a recorded and an
archived live stream so please provide
feedback so we can improve our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we'll follow video etiquette for
live streams head over to active
inference do Institute to learn more
about live streams and other
projects we are in the second in the 58
series Arun and I last week did
58.0 with some background and context
kind of the approach to scratch the
surface and today we're going to pick it
up with
Lance and looking forward to this
discussion so people watching live
please write any live chats Arun has
also prepared a bunch of questions let's
begin though with Lance if you want to
say hi and welcome back and then any any
overviews or any introductions anything
that you feel will help uh set the table
for today thank you
well uh well thank you so much um and
thank you so much for having me so yeah
I'm super excited about this discussion
and I feel a lot of us are trying to
understand renormalizing J the model so
so I'm sure I'm going to learn a lot as
well um yeah so just give a little bit
of background um so now car fisten is
the chief scientific officer at
versus and um one of the challenges that
we we are kind of like moving towards
and and this is public
information is um of course scaling
active
INF and uh there's one particular
challenge that we're looking at it's
Atari um so for those who don't know
Atari is just a suite of um of like
about 30 31 games uh they've been around
for a long time maybe since the 80s or I
don't know exactly it's a famous
benchmark for reinforcement learning now
there's been a lot of work in RL solving
Atari
and maybe stuff even like 10 years old
already that you know solves the T so
the question is why are we trying to do
that with active inference and the
answer is uh all of these RL methods
they use a lot of data they're super
data hungry and they're not uh so they
don't have this human level efficiency
that that we're looking for and so
that's where active inflence could
potentially come into play uh so one of
the things that we're looking at at the
company is scaling active inference to
to show that we can solve aat with human
level
efficiency and and so this scale-free
approach uh planning from pixels emerged
out of these
efforts uh and this has been work led by
call um so he's you know come up with
the ideas and the quote and so forth and
uh
and yeah and and so now we're still
pushing with this approach and and other
approaches so yeah it's super exciting
and um there's many many research
questions of things we could explore uh
so very excited to discuss this
today okay do you want
to give any connective tissue between
some of your previous conversations or
papers or streams
and then we'll jump into the listed
questions we
have um sure so uh so for those who
don't me know me so I'm Lance I've been
working on the pr principal active
influence for a long time uh primarily
on the on the mathematical side of
things so back when I started um uh
possibly the only person understanding
active inflence was car himself and if
you privilege people around c um
and so a lot of the work I I did was to
try to understand things and and put
them on a more rigorous mathematical
footing and so we've had a a few
conversations here um a few live streams
uh speaking about some of that uh so I
would say the the rgm work uh that we're
discussing today is is a bit different
from from what I've been working so far
so um previous work was mostly on the
theory of the 3 princip theory of active
inference to read the math uh today it's
more about a piece of code that does
things and does really cool things uh
also has some interesting
limitations and um so it's a much more
pragmatic agenda and I'm personally
moving in this more pragmatic set of
things uh but I have lot to learn uh yes
so this is this is how things stand at
the
moment yes it was live stream
52 on the geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adaptive
agents that was a great and very uh
epistemic setting and then also now that
I'm seeing
it also
26 so it was sort of a
2652 full card Lance situation but both
of these were some of the clearest and
most fundamental papers and unpacking in
the series um Arun anything you want to
begin with or we can just jump into the
questions you
wrote uh I mean first of all just to say
like I need to catch up on those because
those sound great um also I think some
of my questions are still
fairly like don't to say like at towards
the end of the paper they're much more
like discussion points but I don't know
if maybe for some people who might not
been able to catch the first session
to maybe go into a very high level
summary of the paper
first uh and then set some background
and that might make the discussion
points uh a bit clearer as they happen
uh but very happy to for you to take the
lead on that one
Daniel yeah Lance what would what would
you say is the overall summary through
line and then we'll turn to the specific
questions sure um so should I give a
quick summ
yeah yeah um right so um yeah so so the
problem that we're looking at is
planning from pixels so you have a bunch
of pixels and we want to you know do
decision
making um so for for those who are
familiar with active infs there's
typically two flavors of active imprints
there's the
reflexive type of actor inference where
you're not really planning in the future
but you're like
uh if if I infer that I'm in this state
then I should do this and if I infer I'm
in this state I should do that and it's
typically what we see in continuous
active
inference um and then there's the other
flavor of active inference and also
sophisticated inference which is
typically in the sweet States and um and
that has planning that has expected free
energy has exploration and so
forth um here we are in a setting when
where we are doing things in dispute
States but we are
reflexive uh so this is just to situate
with the other things that are in the
literature and so what happens is we we
get a bunch of pixels so yeah just to go
back a little bit this is um the pixels
the planning paper is a way to learn
from expert
data so if I if if I look at expert data
of an agent doing something I'm going to
be able to learn that with an rgm and
reproduce it in some kind of like a
habitual reflexive Loop but I'm not
going to do any kind of denovo
learning um and and yeah and so then
there's like a very specific um
architecture for the rgm gened model uh
that allows it to do what what it does
and there's a way we can and you know
learn these things but that's kind of
like the BR idea or or at least a
context okay awesome yeah just we have
the figures if there's any to jump to
let's go to the first uh question
so how are renormalizability and
sparsity linked and also if you could
connect that to how else we've seen
sparsity discussed in the Markov blanket
concept what's sparsity in a graphical
model how is renormalizability doing
something similar or different than the
sparsity conditions that we've studied
before right um
so um yeah just to give a bit of a bit
of context on on that question because
you talked about markco blankets so uh K
and and a number of people have this
idea that living systems and I guess
systems in general are made of markup
blankets I mean they are themselves
markup blankets and so if you take an
organism it would be compos composed for
example of organs with their own Mark of
blankets are themselves uh made of cells
with their own Mark of
blankets uh and and you can you know
subdivide uh many many times sort of
zoom in and you'll still see markco
blankets
everywhere and so the what what you get
from that or or probably what called uh
got from that is that there is some kind
of a scale-free invariance about the
nature of things um which is that if you
if you zoom in or if you zoom out and um
you know arbitrary zooming or you
zooming you you would still have this
kind of like fundamental
structure and um and I should say uh the
re normalization group is a mathematical
apparatus for zooming in or zooming out
on things
and and so basically these renormalizing
in models they have this um assumption
that the world is renormalizable that
the world has some kind of spell free
information uh within them and uh and so
we can get more into the details of that
but basically long story short is that
this renormalization aspect it gives you
a very powerful inductive bias on the
structure of your J model
um and in this case it gives you this
kind of renormalizing G model which is a
g model that looks the same at every
scale so it's a gent model that if you
uh you know give it pixel data that's
sort of very zoomed in uh that part of
the model that Fe that data is going to
be the same in in terms of of its
structure that the higher level parts of
the of the model that look at like much
more C grain
features um and and these models are are
very sparse um yeah just because when
you look at the representations in the
model there's many many uh connections
are missing but by Design on purpose
right so so we have a lot of sparse DD
uh so it means that they're very
lightweight um and yeah I would say
that's kind of the main advantage right
uh so when we when we compare with the
traditional machine learning
architectures this is not to say that
you know this approach has a lot of
limitations but one one of the strengths
is that we we get some very lightweight
models that can learn things with a a
relatively low number of
states and and I think that goes back to
sparcity okay let's look at the figure
and and talk about the
architecture
maybe continue a little bit on what what
specifically can can uh where how can we
see that renormalization structure in
figure three and how does this have
similarity and differences than like the
textbook generative models that we've
worked
with right so so I should say a full
disclaimer I don't think the explanation
of renormalizing genal models is very
clear in the
paper and some will say it's extremely
unclear uh so I'm going to try to to
clear some of that
confusion uh but there's also part of it
where where I'm probably still confused
so so apologies an advance if kind of
clear all the
confusion um
but so so I can try to describe the the
figure that you have here and then I can
also give you my own kind of personal
summary of G models of renormalizing gen
models so so here we have kind of um a
classic a classic hierarchical partially
observed Mark of decision process and
the special features is that
um there's a Time Horizon of one at each
layer um and then you you have this
renormalizing scale free aspect where as
you can see at the bottom level you have
two states to actions these are grouped
into one state one action of the level
above and if you go one level even even
further above there's again two states
at the level below and two actions that
are gred into one State and when
actually the level above and you can go
like that for as many layers as you want
um in in the current
code what you do is you specify the
number of layers that that you want uh
to start with and then you would kind of
learn uh you know the transition
mappings and and so on and so
forth what aspects of the code are
available or what languages or timeline
for overall applying
it um you mean for for applying it in
you know to machine learning test is it
is it or or just for any of these
settings what is the code
availability or or what do you think are
the pro the promising ways today and
going forward for people who are
interested in the open source active
inference implementations to work with
it right um yeah so so so I'm not
entirely sure um as to the kind of like
privacy constraints on the on the code
right now um I would assume there's a
link in the paper pointing to a repo but
if that's not the case it's on the case
okay well um so I know it's on a private
version of
SPM and so if it hasn't been released
yet uh then there surely uh talks inside
the company of like when to release it
how to release it um yes I'm not exactly
sure about the timeline of that
unfortunately okay all good yeah I mean
the it's it's an
interesting meta piece with the research
and being able to share that and with
this information here from the pseudo
code it it gives a lot of the recipe and
the anatomy of of the uh model but let
me just uh
is there is there another part of this
figure or another figure to continue
specifying a little bit more about
what's happening or do we want to jump
back to the
questions um yeah so uh there's a
presentation by by Tim ferin that that
I'm um and there's a useful slide on
that presentation uh that that could
potentially show I don't know if I can
share my screen here but I think it
would be quite useful to illustrate a
bit more what's going on oh yeah share
your screen and
uh so see if I can do that this is a new
[Music]
computer okay yeah unfortunately I'm not
going to be able to do it because it's
um
I mean I could but I need to fit away
the settings or you could you could
email it and I don't have admin rates
okay you could email any slides um if
you wanted to to admin yeah I'll check
I'll check and yeah I'll get back to you
on that but but I can I'm happy to
explain yeah continue what what I was
going to show so the idea and and here
I'm going to have to wave my hands a bit
but hopefully it's it's clear so
um you you get some pixel data you get a
movie basically that's what rgms do you
get a movie of an agent doing something
and you're going to learn a gen model
that you know learns that and is able to
reproduce the agent in the movie and so
it's able to learn its actions and and
reproduce its actions depending on the
state so the way it works is you um you
take one frame of the movie and you take
the next frame
and and this would be like your lowlevel
observation for the renormalizing D
model so why do we take two consecutive
frames uh as one observation it's
because we want to extract position but
also
momentum uh
information um so so that's our
observation two consecutive frames then
each frame we're going to um we're going
to divide it into several overlapping
patches
so this like a convolution on your
network with
so um yeah you have like multiple
patches that overlap each Centered for
example around
pixel and then each of those patches you
do a singular value
decomposition which is that you uh you
take the Aron vectors you have those
pixel vectors you take the iron
vectors and and you essentially do a PCA
and and the reason why you do that so so
just to give a little bit of a context
um well first of all uh planning is is
much easier in discret
States uh so somehow things work a lot
better or see or at least that's what we
think at this moment uh so want to
convert this kind of like very high
dimensional kind of continuous data that
are pixels into some more uh manageable
size uh low dimensional dispute
representation that we can then work
with in the
rgm and so there's potentially many ways
you could do that and one way would be
to use a like kind of a for example um a
varation encoder where you would then
discretize the laden space that would be
one way to get from continuous discrete
there's many many ways uh you can do
this step the reason why iOS C chose SVD
is because it's very
lightweight and it's also very um I
would say context sensitive if you give
one bit of data will adapt to that data
to give it another bit of data will
adapt as well um there's arguably also
pred using a deep learning architecture
the cons is that it would need to be
trained so lots to explore there but for
now we use
SVD and so um so once you've done your
your singular value DEC composition you
get these igen vectors that um just get
a list of igen vectors for for each
patch that tell you okay well this is
like the most important
feature in in the patch of pixel this is
second most important feature third most
important feature and so forth what you
do is you turn that so you take the most
important feat
features and then you discretize that um
so it's it's a lot of steps um I know so
hopefully I can send you a picture but
the point is that you extract the
features using SVD so you get a much
lower dimensional representation of the
data and because you trate it you kind
of eliminate the noise you eliminate the
things you don't care and then this low
dimensional thing which is still
continuous because these are AG vectors
you can bti it using multiple bins so
now you have disc
data and once you have your discreete
data then you can fit it to the picture
that you have in the slide right there
and do your heral NDP um kind of like
much more
classic yeah awesome yeah in thezero we
talked a little bit about that process
about going from The Continuous to the
discrete to enable planning over the
discretized form ER go for it
yeah I mean thanks for that summary L it
was really like clear and informative uh
one question I have just to follow off
from that is when you something you said
quite early on which is that planning in
the continuous Space is really difficult
um could you say a little bit about why
that is so the reason I ask is I think
it's a very common thing that people
would want to do is have an agent that
can plan an action to do this thing but
control the degree at which it does it
so I would like to move but by a certain
amount how do I choose how much to move
in a continuous distance so I guess
maybe could you say a little bit about
why it's so difficult to plan in
continuous
space it's um it's a really good
question so I think um so planning is
always about doing things um so when
when I talk about planning I don't talk
specifically about action selection I
talk about imagining what will happen
um you know in a certain time interval
in the future so it means that you're
looking at what would happen if I did
that in terms of what is the trajectory
of what would happen if I did that now
if you're in discrete space discrete
time you're looking at a sequence of
future
States but if you're in um and and so
your space of trajectories that you're
kind of like planning over is discrete
because like um possible steps at the
next time set and then transable step
next time step so it can be huge bit
discreet when you're in continuous space
if you want to plan uh in a certain time
interval in the future you're looking at
trajectories of what would happen if you
took a particular trajectory of actions
and so if you're in continuous space
continuous time the space of
trajectories is infin
dimensional so I think that's kind of
like the well it's infinite and also
infinite dimensionals it's kind of like
really
that and
yeah and there probably I mean there are
algorithms that kind of do this I'm not
really an expert on that but I think
that's kind of like the underlying
limitation the the fundament fundamental
mathematical limitation and so the thing
you can do then uh to plan in continuous
space continuous time is you abstract
away on a discrete space and then and
then you go back down and and this is
what what we we've been doing I mean as
you know um in active inference it's
kind of like the the hack there's
probably other ways to do it but yeah
that's where we're
at so maybe something just to clarify
there is the nature of these Infinities
right so you said infinite
dimensional but then also it's almost
like infinite values for each of those
Dimensions so that's why it gets really
explosive in the number of things you
have to consider uh one of the things
that we talked about in the Z was the
path-based
formulation and how that seemed to be
even more combinations you would have to
consider compared to the textbook uh
formulation where now we're considering
paths Over States and actions and there
are as
many uh combinations of Paths of like
com combinate combining States and
action choices uh which already sounded
like
quite difficult to solve relative to
sort of the toy examples of just what
what's in the book so maybe you could uh
say a little bit about that right so so
just to make sure I'm on the same page
with you um what what do you mean
exactly by the path based
formulation so I think it's um when
we're now
to just figure 4.3 from the textbook is
kind of a good touch point on the top is
the discrete time explicit States and
observations at time points are
considered time Point 1 2 3 4 in
continuous
time future time points are only
predicted through a tailor series
generalized coordinates expansion which
is something we talked about in in
52 um or continue from there just wanted
to bring in those two textbook figures
and how they can be combined in in a
hybrid architecture that kind of prees
what we're talking about today
yeah okay that's it's interesting that
you bring up J coordinates because
um yeah I when I when I was mentioning
myopic active inference or like not
using pass um I wasn't specifically
mentioning referring to generalized
coordinates kind of like the more
simpler version without the generalized
coordinates because you're right you're
absolutely right that when you have
journalized
coordinates uh
you you do get trajectories again the
the difference or or one of the
differences is in discrete States um you
you may have a limited computational
budget that can limits you in several
ways but at least theoretically you can
plan infinitely or arbitrarily far ahead
in the
future uh even though your beliefs would
get very
imprecise um in continuous States when
you have generalized coordinates you
have this notion of um encoding implicit
trajectories in the future through these
tailor expansions but the Tor expansions
are only by Design only going to be
accurate on a very small or or small uh
time interval so so already
theoretically if you have only finally
many journalized grat which is what you
always have in practice you're not able
to plan veryify in the future very this
is
um this is like much more sophisticated
than than any kind of active inference
without the generalized coordinates or
the things I was mentioning
before the yeah one other thing um is so
so when you do planning in the sweet
States here like comparing multiple
trajectories of
actions if I remember right but but
correct me here in I'm if morong when
you do planning in the continuous state
for generalized coordinates so the at
the bottom of 4.3 you always minimizing
the gradient of the free energy with
your
actions so even though you
plan the the trajectories of states in
the future if you did that you don't
plan for sequences of
actions I I believe that that's true or
another way to say that is that the
continuous time formal Iz ation even if
you do have a high
degree uh tailor series expansion or a
lot of generalized coordinates it isn't
explicitly considering counterfactual
scenarios like tree surch in chess it's
like seven moves down the road if 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 then 8 a 8 B 8 C whereas in a
continuous time expansion you get one
polom approximator but it isn't saying
well what if time .12 were different all
you could say is something about the
statistics of that path as
interpolated but you wouldn't be able to
directly um make strong guarantees
outside of following the gradients
around that inferred
path so maybe maybe I've mistaken
something but I either in one of the
points that you've written there Daniel
or something GL said I remember the word
reflexive for The Continuous time AC of
inference is that is that what we're
saying here is that um yeah there we go
without planning um at least with A
continuous um time
formulation yes it's sort of doing
something with the expectation of what's
going to happen in the future B you say
it's not considering counterfactuals
we're not considering if I do this then
this if I go 10 m rather than 20 MERS
this will happen
Etc yeah
yeah I think if it would be interesting
if you if you as that question to call
if he if he draws the same distinction
but but I would totally agree with you I
would say so at the beginning I was
referring to continuous active inference
without the J coordinates as being
reflexive I would say that with jiz
coordinates it's still reflexive but
you're right that it's still it's
already much more sophisticated in a
sense yeah the generalized coordinates
are like a way to bring the depth
in it's like doing momentum trading on a
stock over multiple time scales you're
still making an instantaneous decision
in the sense you're looking at a vector
of the current moment and then looking
at different Trends and first second
third Etc higher moments however again
there's not explicit planning so this
sort of gets into the
functional underpinnings of anticipatory
behavior and whether anticipatory
Behavior can be loaded up into a sort of
reflexive intuitive moment or Andor to
what extent it involves explicit tree
based search of branching
possibilities yes totly
um okay but just to to close the loop on
The Spar on the
sparsity could we say generative models
are defined by their sparsity we're
literally talking about some set of
random variables nodes and their edges
which defines their sparity conditions
any node interpolating between two other
nodes is a blanket people often are
interested in the agent environment
blanket as interface however taking the
graphical model as as a base graph
itself we can think about the B Matrix
here as being a blanket um for example
between these other two nodes um the
sparity conditions of figure three and
the re I mean whatever model you design
the connectivity is the sparsity
condition renormalization generative
models have a special template or recipe
for how the sparsity conditions are
related within an across
levels okay Arun want to pick one of
these or which one to go to
next um I actually think the next one is
they're sort of roughly in an
order uh so yeah I think talking about
the RG operators because it is the
really new thing in this paper what
makes a good
one what makes a good RG
operator
so um yeah I mean I'm assuming if you
ask this question you probably know more
about RG operators and I do um so it' be
interesting to know what you think about
this um yeah to be honest like uh yeah
just just to give like a comment uh
this is one of the things I really need
to read up on
um K repeatedly
says there is this Universal aspect to
rizing Joint models and I agree that
there is some part of nature that seems
to be scale free in terms of like these
markco blankets at different scales but
to me there is also a lot of nature that
is not scale free I mean not everything
that you look at is a fractal
so in what sense are rgms
Universal uh the super cool thing and
surprising thing for me in this paper is
that there's a lot of things that you
can do with rgm there's a lot of things
that you can learn I'm not sure it's
what extent I mean I I would really like
to know okay well this is one thing that
you cannot do with rgms in terms of like
uh I canot memorize this yeah that's
something I'm not I'm not sure about
so maybe I can sort of come back on that
uh so I think the use of the SVD and
effectively principal components
analysis and this paper is actually like
a really nice introduction to
renormalization groups if you don't know
what they if you haven't heard of them
before uh it's very common in other
aspects of more like traditional pattern
matching and machine learning uh and
there's loads of good tutorials uh just
out on the web we've got a couple of
Linked In the slides uh to explain what
it does so I think just saying like to
summarize that very quickly PCA is uh
you do a transformation on your data to
maximize variance amongst particular
dimensions and then you can do a
dimensionality reduction by throwing
away the dimensions you don't want so
that really neatly leads into the
definition of rgms in this paper which
is the core scening it's the critical
part is that you are throwing bits away
that you think aren't important at
particular levels and then as you go up
levels you throw away different
dimensions but they feed into the lower
levels uh but I think it's there's also
a lot of talk in this paper about like
the spin block transformation as well of
how the pixels are sort of blocked up
and then you say okay we're going to co
grain in space uh and also course
graining in time that's in a couple of
the examples in the paper as well uh but
I guess my sort of question is
particularly on the like how do we know
our cor scening is not throwing away
actually useful
information and how does that relate to
the data that we're putting into the
training as well uh I think that's
because I know you mentioned before this
is all about learning from expert play
but are we also possibly throwing away
some of the expertise when we C
grade totally um yeah totally I mean um
as far as things stand at the moment
this is more of a open question a
research question so some of the things
that we're we're doing is you know
testing rgms on on different kind of of
expert play for different games or for
different environments uh in and outside
of Atari and looking at how well it
works um so my own take right now is
that rgms are pretty good at memorizing
uh really a bunch of things a bunch of
expert
play the well two things um
the for for rgms to do well the the game
or the environment needs to have some
kind of orbits some kind of um orbit
structure that um yeah the RG GM would
learn so that's like one thing that's
pretty important the main challenge of
rgm that that we've kind of been looking
at or or looking into is
generalizability so one of the things
that uh we show in the paper which is
pretty cool I think is this uh Dove
example so we we learn this Dove video
with the rgm and then we include uh the
Dove and the rgm is able to infer o um
I'm actually so it's going back to its
training data it's reconstruction of the
training data and reconstructing the
dove um that's one type of
generalization that works very well but
it kind of highlights um perhaps I mean
what what seems to be a drawback as well
so the
RGN uh learns representations of the
training data which means that when you
expose it to non-training data so such
as the dog which is uded it will go back
to training data and be like okay well
this is the do that I saw in my training
and so I'm going to reconstruct
it what if um you train it on Expert
play for a game or expert something for
something and then you initialize the
rgm at a different condition so let's
say um so uh let's say you train the rgm
on walking data some robot walking the G
will learn the orbits of walking and you
will be able to reconstruct the motion
and the actions of walking but now if
you initialize the argm of like I'm
lying flat on the ground it won't be
able to stand up to go back on the
Walking orbit it will infer that it's
walking and it would execute the actions
of walking even though it's flat on the
ground so you can imagine the motion um
the motion that you get out of it um and
this is um kind of a generalization
aspect where rgms are really lacking is
if you're outside of the training data
you're going to infer that you're in
your training data when in fact that
you're not how do you go back to the
things that you've learned how do you
pick up the
orbit yeah this this definitely came up
in the previous one the point zero as
well Daniel we're talking about
resiliency of models um
and uh this is I think a really
interesting question of yeah how do you
know if you're out of distribution
if you like there are there are other
sort of machine learning applications
ofbe like colal density estimation or
whatever where you might say okay I've
trained on this data I get this new data
can I compare it to probability
distribution and say oh wait this
doesn't look like anything else that
I've seen
before hit I'm now very uncertain on
what to do is there a way we could apply
those sorts of principles
here yeah I supposed so um so this is um
this would be a very interesting project
because um yeah I mean this is the main
limitation with rgms right now and uh
yeah there's possibly many routes
forward but um yeah the moment that's
the main challenge so taking inspiration
from the things that he mentioned would
be super
promising one one way that um active
inference models at least have a
diagnostic is surprise bounded by
variational free energy does give you a
measure of overall How likely something
is apt to be so if you have a um
training on driving safely then you're
minimally surprised by the safe drive
you have a measure at least this kind of
threat agnostic measure of something
different is
happening however it's almost a general
information Theory
problem of well H the space of what you
don't know is always going to be so much
lar there's always more that you could
be surprised by like for all the
combinations of valid English sentences
that language models are trained on
there are more combinations of gibberish
sequences so then how how to make
something that can weave its way back
into the orbital zone or into a zone of
control and that's that's where some of
the multiscale architectures and
switching
architectures come into
play because the
the variational free energy value itself
isn't going to say what to do when the
car is
off-road but at least it would be a
diagnostic of how like a kernel D
density estimator how
similar it is to training
information just the another thing to
bring in as well I think we're sort of
bringing all the questions in at once
but uh it's all it's all related and
it's all relevant um the question of how
if we are only training these things on
Expert play uh how can we create
resilient agents that can recover from
unseen positions to so quote unquote get
back on the path
so I think one of the things that came
to my mind when I was reading the paper
was if you give it data where it starts
off in a losing position and you can
show it ways of going ah if you are
losing this is how you get to
winning then that would become a new
potential attractor set that okay if I
am losing I can then move to another
sets where I'm winning so you explicitly
give it that Journey as data that it
sees but then I think we come on to one
of my other questions which is how do we
then tell an agent that has learned the
structure from the data
itself which attractor sets are good and
which are bad how do we inject value
into these to say okay we've given you
this data where let's say the
self-driving car is a really nice
example driving safely is great if you
are in an accident and you drive Offroad
this is how you get back onto the path
but if it's learned the structure of
those actions from the data itself how
do we then inject the value that
actually driving safely is good and
being Offroad is
bad yeah I mean uh yeah really
interesting questions um so so I have a
few thoughts that I think Echo what you
said I don't have specific
Solutions uh but just to Echo what you
said so for example in the case of
walking uh we might ask okay well if we
have the training data for for walking
agent and and somehow the the agent is
like down either sitting or or lying
down uh we should teach it how to stand
up and then once once it's recovered
this starting position it can go back
and use the rgm policy so that's one
solution um uh yeah going back to to the
starting point of of the orbit that that
works um and but but there are there
there are challenges so for
example and this is maybe a slightly
different challenge but also coming back
to self-driving
cars um a self-driving car is a very
very high dimensional system lots of
moving Parts actions uh things that are
going
on um so if you if you give the rgm a
lot of uh a lot of driving data of
driving safely I'm assuming the rgm
would would learn in comfortably but now
if you Expos it to a new situation it
hasn't seen before in the in the
training set and I would assume this
would just happen very easily right
because we're such in a in um in a very
very high dimensional space and when you
think about it it's kind of a paral
dimensionality problem because you're
feeding trajectories to the rgm so
trajectories or or orbits these are
onedimensional
objects and you're in a state space
could be very high dimensional for
example in the in a St driving card and
what you want is to get full coverage of
like the underlying manifold of uh State
Driving um and and what you also want is
if you're in an unsafe driving situation
you want the trajectory that gets you
back to the manifold of cell driving so
you have these two problems um and
and yeah so one problem coming back to
the curse of dimensionality is that if
you have this extremely high dimensional
manifold of save driving you want to
cover it with onedimensional
trajectories the higher the dimension
the harder it's going to be because
you're in
a trying to cover a large n dimensional
thing with onedimensional
objects so computationally it's going to
be a
problem um and and yeah so there this
generalization that doesn't work like
within as you said like within uh data
distribution generalization that's a
problem because if if you give it a lot
of data of the driving safely situation
we would wanted to kind of extrapolate
over all uh safe scenarios of
driving and we don't we don't really see
that at the moment or at least uh maybe
it happens but it could be a challenge
uh in some situations and the other one
which is maybe the more fundamental
problem is you have this huge region of
driving not safely how do you go back to
driving safely situation also coming
back to the example of walking how how
does that happen and and that's also
very hard right because potentially we
would want to you know have a trajectory
back to the safe situation from every
possible starting location but as the
state space becomes very large that also
becomes very difficult
Co yeah when thinking about all the
angles your joints could be in all the
muscle energies that there might be a
very
small
zone so how how to really think about
adaptive active inference agents at the
agentic level and then also more at the
systems design level how could
components
be robust and
adaptive and simplified components doing
better on a
subtask and then
design a composed system where the sort
of low
energy efficacious operation of the
smaller units is designed in a way where
where they are not dealing with that
massive over all computational challenge
they're dealing with local computational
challenges however that moves
the design challenge to um or or moves
the the functional challenge to design
time rather than inference
time but most morphologies don't walk
but if you have one that walks through
through Evolution or whatnot then it may
be a relatively simp simplified
inference problem at
runtime however the challenge is
basically figuring out which of those
sparsities and message passing schemes
would result in tractable node level
inference otherwise it it would be hard
to do on a relevant
hardware and and adding to that if I may
so going back to um the walking example
that mentioned and also the uh
generalizing within data distribution
so um there there is uh evidence and
that's also something that we've kind of
encountered empirically that walking is
a chaotic
orbit which means that if you so let's
say I'm here and I'm going to take some
actions and I walk now let's say I start
from a slightly
different uh infin different uh initial
condition and I take the exact same
actions I'm going to fall at some
point and that's like the chaoticity
right so if you take the same actions
but you start from a three different
initial condition you're going to
diverge very far away at some point and
so we have um and I think we have this
problem in our GM that if we teach the
agent to go back to the standing
position and then take the rgm policy if
the agent has a slightly different
initial condition than what the rgm was
trained on the rgm will infer that it is
in the true starting position even
though it's slightly different and then
it will take the actions of the rgm and
it will fall at some
point so you have this idea that just
memorizing uh just doesn't work in that
situation and and yeah that's also an
issue
so maybe I just just a small question
there is the issue there that with the
course graining part in that a slight
change in initial conditions is being
thrown away by the PCA and throwing away
Dimensions early on and then when we go
back and do the inference we infer that
we are sort of in quote unquote the same
place because we've thrown away like
something that we've is actually
signaled has gone to the noise part of
this yeah I imagine that's one way to
look at it um the the way I've been
looking at it but I haven't think been
thinking about it in in those terms is
um just if you're training data is one
particular um you know orbit trajectory
and and you start slightly different
because you're inferring where you are
based on the training data based on the
structure that you've learned you're
going to infer that you're on your right
trajectory even though you're not and
you're going to reproduce that but
you're going to land arbitrarily far um
but yeah I see it's the same
[Music]
phenomenon this kind of gets to the
whole structure
determination
question um chaotic systems are
sensitive to small changes near critical
points but then there might be another
zone of the system that isn't so
susceptible to critical points so like
let's look at the chaotic attractor
example from the
paper
um in figure
13 if we were to make a small change
while we were out on one of the arms of
the attractor it might not change things
that much but then there might be some
other points where it it does lead to um
taking a
bifurcation so so if you can break
up systems so that the core graining
captures those
bifurcations into two discrete
categories
then it discretizes a continuous chaotic
system well but then if you are applying
a grid that's in conasur it with what's
actually happening then any grid you
draw is going to include trajectories
that that have radically different
outcomes so the overall predictive
efficacy or the variance retention of
the SVD is going to be
low like if there's actually
two Z zones in a city and they're one
mile squared and they have different
properties and you have a one M grid and
you actually capture it you you carve
nature at the joints or articulate it at
the joints but if every
block has mixed zoning and all you have
is a on M Grid it's that you could do
the best placement of your one mile grid
but it still is always going to capture
something that's kind of
mixed and this kind of related to a few
of our thoughts and questions
like how how do we
determine what window to use just just
from a generic
perspective like there was 10 levels in
the discretization of a grayscale image
or there was a
4x4 or the mnist images were
pre-processed to to 32x 32
pixels and then they were blocked in 4x4
grids so how
much sweeping or how do you do inference
on the number of
discretizations and the and the window
size and all these other
features like what kinds of tradeoffs
computationally do you look for or how
many levels of
meta
modeling do you feel like are relevant
to engage in when you could sweep across
discretization
of N and windows of M and then you could
have well window size of six with a
discretization of three gives this
performance but something so H how do
you even navigate through that
combinatorics yeah um and yeah really
good question so yeah at the moment it's
very much um and because this is very
much a new thing um for the moment these
are hyper parameters and we very much in
the exploratory phase of
um okay well this works and this doesn't
work um I mean I'm assuming for I'm
thinking for the paper there wasn't much
hyperparameter tuning like it was all
you know power powers of two that were
chosen and a small number of
layers um but when you think about it I
mean you could uh do rization by powers
of three powers of four um you could
choose to have smaller or bigger
patches um increase or decrease the
number of patches so so there's many
things you can be looking at um and I
would say that's also a problem that you
would get if you were to do structure
learning with Gen of models that are not
specifically renormalizing gen models
you also have that problem of okay how
many patches how many layers and so
forth um so this is not a problem that's
like specific to this approach what this
approach has which makes the problem a
lot easier is um that there is a lot of
um interplay between the number of
layers and the number of patches right
uh so if you choose I'm going to
renormalize by by two so means that um
two states at one level become one state
at the next level and two states at that
level become one state at the next level
this this gives you a relationship
between the number of states and the
number of layers that you have and also
implicitly the number of patches that
you have so you have um so you have this
like big constraint that comes in
renormalizing G models that makes the
search a lot simpler than otherwise but
I think ultimately uh what you would
probably want is to infer I think we
hinted that infer like the number of
patches and and so forth um yeah we're
not doing that it would be Co to do
that I think another possible thing we
could try is maybe start with a budget
of this
many layers
patches um like basically combinatorics
and set okay you have this much
computational power for understanding
this data
figure out the best way of allocating
that because at some levels you might
have more variability than others and
maybe you want to allocate your
computational budget at the higher
abstract levels and you do more so than
you want to do at the pixel level and
perhaps we could learn that from the
data itself given a constraint of this
many parameters and I think you could
probably code that up multiple ways but
one way you could have priors on those
hyper parameters and then I think it's
Daniel suggested in the point Z do a
free energy uh calculation on that uh
compared to that your PRI on those type
of parameters and just minimize free
energy that way um but you could also
probably do a hacky approach as well and
just go well we'll give me the best
performance call it
there yeah and and just to um kind of
echo that and complement that so as you
as you both mentioned the issue is well
there's so many hyperparameters I me
there's so many quote unquote right
because if we're using gen models that
we're not rizing there would be even
more of them uh but even here we we have
a lot of um hyper parameters and and so
that's um a separate thing that that
we're also working on which is can we
infer the structure of the
model uh instead of just saying oh well
we have this data this is the model that
we get um I think we need to be
recognizing the fact that with limited
data you're always going to be unsure
about the uh the resulting model and so
we need to have uh probability
distributions of
models and so one one instance of that
is what mentioned like we have
probability distribution a prior over
the number of patches and we optimize
that with respect to free
energy uh but we could also have
probability distributions over as three
layers or four layers and so for
um and I think this is where we this is
kind of
um I mean uh yeah be Beyond this paper
but what we need to be going is having
uncertainty about the model and so then
if I have uncertainty about the model I
can take actions upon the world that
maximize the expected Information Gain
about the model so I'm going to get data
that's maximally informative to refine
my beliefs ultimately convert verging
about the best model of the world or or
maybe a set of candidate bests if there
is a fundamental obstruction where you
cannot find which one fits best um but
the point is in this approach to
structure learning and I think in every
other approach that we have in active so
far we're not recognizing the inherent
uncertainty about the
model and so what we're doing in
the um yeah in all these uh structure
learning approaches is is is a kind
of um well imagine if you have a prior
of models then if you have data you have
implicity posterior
models now this is what I think we need
to do and what we're currently doing
implicitly by taking the model with the
lowest free energy when we actually do
that is taking a flat prior models and
then taking the most likely model in the
posterior so we're doing this maximum a
posterior estimation when we're
optimizing model free
energy
um and yeah ultimately we would want to
have a distribution of a models and also
recognize that a priori models are more
likely than
others that's funny about having a flat
prior over models it's almost like
Return of the
frequentism all models within this class
are equally likely so that's the special
case of basanis where it's sort of anron
istically is frequentist again because
then you're selecting the maximum
likelihood model
structure or waiting model Reliance in a
portfolio on
its maximum likelihood
estimation but then rather than using an
ml value the the model itself is
actually engaging in a basian inference
process
um how about representations of
uncertainty within the model like just
taking a given architecture as fixed I'm
curious
about how are uncertainties represented
there was some discussion of lossless
and lossy
compression and and do we have any way
to to
have
interpretability of the uncertainties
across
layers like do you find that you can
trace those State estimations and
uncertainty estimates and they ring true
or once we're past the pixel level is
through the SVD and all of this are we
already in spaces that are not human
semantically
interpretable um good question so yeah
coming back to to one of the points that
Aron made um because we we do this SVD
and we throw away the comp some like
less relevant
components uh we are throwing away
information and so we're always in this
losty compression uh kind of
setting uh now what we've done in this
paper and also in other
experiments is to just try to
reconstruct expert play or any other
kind of video or agent from the rgm and
usually works pretty well so we as you
can see with the dove or with many other
examples um the rgm does a good job at
compressing and
reconstructing um but we haven't
actually look into mechanistic
interpretability of like this um this
state in the rgm actually enclosed this
and this St in rgm actually includes
that so that would be interesting to to
look into
I think in the Mist
example there is a a little section
where where it said like okay at the
very top level we say there's basically
a value per class of Digit which feels
very much alike okay we've in the
intermediate stuff it's very
uninterpretable but at the end we're
going to have okay we're going to say
each of these scale each of these uh
values at the top level can have
correspond to a digit because we're
designing a
classifier uh it's a I think it's a
really interesting question that's not
just specific to this paper or to act of
inference I think it's to semi supervise
or sorry self-supervised learning in
general which is how do you interpret
that if you're learning the structure of
data from the data without anything
labeled how do you get that
interpretability
um and I don't think there's an easy
answer to that yeah like does so here at
level four okay so so
um this this also notes the matrices in
this figure are not simple likelihood
mappings they're concatenated likelihood
mappings from all hidden States at one
level to all hidden States and paths at
the subordinate level where the sum to
one constraint is applied to States each
child could be in so we're
taking some higher
level path trajectory
and pulling lower level observations
from a probability distribution some
some to one at that lower level for the
child so here at the top
level there's
states so it's almost like if you came
across an alien handwritten text how
would you know how many letters there
were or if there was several writers
with different styles
how how would you say how many discrete
symbols is that's kind of like this
unstructured or semi structured learning
question you have cursive handwriting
from a language where you don't know how
many discrete symbols there are you know
there's a discrete
compositionality at the level of the
word let's just say however you're
getting the raw data and then the pl the
pixels to planning in the linguistic
case or the phonemes to planning is like
how do you go from continuous visual or
sound data to inference and planning
over language
production but
then you don't know how many discrete
elements to
have per se but if you can have a if you
can be making a domain specific model
that may not be a relevant question you
may just be able to say we know we're
going to get to 10 find me the best
10 but it's it's interesting that that
the
um compositionality of the rgm could
extend to higher orders of
structure with the trade-off that
there's just more and more as you
continue to expand how many states there
can be it doesn't escape the curse of
dimensionality it's like swimming in the
cursive
dimensionality or casting the spell of
the cursive
dimensionality but at least in a way
where the model architecture is going to
be able to be implemented
using the inference methods that
are the same across different
scales quick question on that do we
think that the PCA part of this
could give you a clue as to how many
values a particular State could have in
a layer if you said I think Daniel you
had this idea in the point zero of
saying well maybe we just have as many
values a state could occupy that
explains 80% of the variance at that
level so then you could say then I mean
we're sort of moving the complexity from
this part into construction of the
training data which we should definitely
talk about uh at some point that's cool
um but you could then
say yeah exactly that's that's the graph
I wanted um if we're going to just aior
say I I only need to explain 80% of the
variance on this stuff Chuck some
training data at it and then we say oh
this training data had like 10 digits
and then you basically end up picking 10
values because that explains enough
variance in the training data to do the
good a good enough job
yeah for sure and I I would say um that
so simplicit what happens when we're
optimizing model free energy right
because we're trading off uh accuracy
and
complexity and um what you're mentioning
maybe like a more deliberate way of
saying well we have this target um what
what is the minimally complex model to
to achieve this Target for example and
um yeah yeah that would be super cool to
do I think specifically for more like
engineering and Industry applications
that that would be something that people
would be very interested in because um
for example Regulators they don't talk
in terms of oh your free energy should
have lower than this value and then you
can use your model for sell driving
cards right you're approved uh it's more
like oh want some some kind of act re
see some kind of explanation of some
data about a thir threshold and yeah it
would be very worthwhile for this kind
of
application yeah how to how to convert
from a sort
of model intrinsic currency the way that
different structural models are compared
with each other or the way that
alternative parameterizations are
compared within the same active
inference model through comparison of
their free energy values how to convert
that
into a value or a currency that
matters like an actual risk profile or a
cost or a time
estimate that's the critical question
how how does the
reliability of the inference
translate
um what would be an interesting way to
go Lance and then for those in the live
chat please feel free to write some
specific questions and I'll
ask sorry um specific interesting way to
go for way or just what do you feel like
we should continue with or oh yeah okay
H also H how do how do others pick up
and continue with this work Beyond
studying the background 11 and a half
phds needed to continue with
this knowing that better and more
advanced open source tools are under
acave development here and elsewhere but
I
mean what what's the way to engage with
this material with the current state or
what are your next plans for how it
continues from this pre-print
form yeah um so good question um I think
there's already a lot of um ideas that
have come up in this PO um I think one
interesting idea is um what what Arun
mentioned like using tools from machine
learning to improve generalizability in
rgms um more
broadly my personal takehome message uh
because we we've been talking a lot
about uh well first of all how our GMS
work but also what the limitations are
so um this is my understanding is that
this is a very new kind of model and
there are a lot of
limitations
um but there there is the like the recol
thing about this paper and and this is
why I'm personally excited about rgms is
this uh universality
claim um the fact that uh rgms are super
expressive you have this like one
architecture that can learn many many
things that are pixel based as we' seen
in the
paper and uh so this is what we've seen
empirically uh here and in other places
then there's the more theoretical reason
for why that's the case and I would say
that's more of a physics question of
like understanding uh renormalizing
groups and why the world may be or May
not be renormalizable to some
extent uh so I think it would be super
cool from the theoretical perspective to
have a better understanding of that from
um an applied
perspective uh so we've seen all these
limitations um and it was already clear
on this call that for each of these
limitations we don't know
exactly whether it's a fundamental
limitation whether the limitation lies
from from the current
implementation or maybe from the current
instance of rgms but we can modify them
in some clever way to actually overcome
the
limitation so there's many different
places where improvements could
come um code uh the the actual uh
structure of of the thing or maybe even
the theory maybe we need more than
renormalizing D models Maybe
renormalizing is not all you need you
need something else so at the moment I
think we should be you know looking at
where each of those limitations uh are
and you know how to go forward from
there um the other thing is classical
active infint like the discrete planning
is does actual planning you know it's it
plans multiple steps ahead and it has
this counterfactual aspect in know GM
you don't have that you just learn the
transitions from state to state at each
level and then you infer them from the
data you're just like you're like in
this uh self-fulfilling prophecy mode
where you've seen your training data and
you're reproducing that from the
rgm and it would be cool
to know if you can combine the strength
of classical active inference and the
rgms to have some planning at one or
multiple levels some actual planning
with Information Gain to actually help
um this um generalization
aspect by by improving the model with
some you know new relevant data so so
there's many many uh you know uh
directions this work could be taken in
uh personally the direction I'm most
excited in is this idea of moral
uncertainty because
in so I I mean a big question in in
machine learning and also developmental
cognitive science is this idea of
structure learning how do you learn the
structure of your model of the world now
there's a lot of um papers evidence and
and I think there's also a lot of debate
but uh one interesting Paradigm is this
idea of model
inference and
uh the way we've been thinking about
structure learning in active inference
so far is about optimizing model free
energy so we take the model that that
has the lowest free energy when we do
that we are frequent we are basian in
the states and parameters but we are
frequentist in the model and that goes
exactly to what we were saying before uh
this idea that you have this flat prior
and you're doing maximum at posterior
estimation and so we know that being
frequentis is fine but you can uh this
means that you can
overfit um it means uh yeah basically
you're selecting a model structure that
overfits that best fits of data and
which may overfit you're not recognizing
any kind of
uncertainty and there's actually a lot
of
theorems that show that uh with limited
data but even unlimited data there's
many instances where uh multiple models
could explain the data equally well
which means that they would have the
same free
energy now which one do you
pick and and two different models could
yield two different decisions so if
you're in a real world scenario one
model may be you know the true model or
what we want the agent to have the other
one would be wrong and could have some
you know unsafe decisions being made
down the
line um so what what we want to be
moving to is this idea of full model
inance not just uh not just map
estimation but actually having a full
posterior of models and this would be
for example a particle approximate
posterior where you entertaining A
mixture of models and so basically means
that you would be doing Bas mod
averaging for all your of your
predictions and and yes so we we want to
be moving towards that in my opinion and
what this affords which I think is super
important is so when you have this um
uncertainty about models you have this
idea of taking actions that maximize the
expected Information Gain about your
model and and so now you can start to
learn your model in a self-supervised
way and hopefully in a way that also
generalizes because you're making this
epistemic search that informs your model
which we're currently not doing at the
moment we're seeking data that's
informative for the states and
parameters and we're overfitting the
model and we going to be moving beyond
that awesome yeah very interesting it's
like equivalent to only doing policy
selection on pragmatic value is just
utility seeking so then if the utility
of the modeler is model fit they have
entered into a pragmatic only
analytic
mode that in single-minded pursuit of
what appears to be a totally valid
defensible analytic goal of accuracy or
of data poster posterior
fit
ironically
produces
local
overfitting so it's like exactly why we
use expected free energy for policy
inference because it does have the
epistemic value component and then now
with this level among portfolios of
models it's like we need to remember why
we put the epistemic value into the
architecture at the base layer because
it isn't enough to just have the
epistemics at the base layer and then
forget about it at the modeler level
there's actually a role for the
epistemic value and the and and also for
the lifelong
learning whereas in the examples here
there was a training phase and then a
test
phase as opposed to like sleep
wake type train and test and updating
with online
inference like if the rules of the game
changed or something like
that yeah totally yes you want to be
able to handle
environments say uh going back to to
games because I guess we love games but
it doesn't have to be games let's say
you're in a an environment uh and you
learn how to play the environment you
learn the Gen of model and then you you
get to the end of the level you get to a
new level and the environment changes
somehow the number of categories changes
and so forth you want to be able to
handle that in a in a graceful way and
you want to be able to handle the
inherent uncertainty about the
world um so there's a lot of um worked
on AI driven scientific discovery and
you can already that I mean science is
about understanding the mechanisms that
generate the data that we have and in
particularly the mechanisms of cause and
consequence right what causes what among
our Laten States so this is
like a totally uh I mean like an example
that all of us can relate of the fact
that we have uncertainty about Cal
structure and we may also have
uncertainty about the number of
representations
uh used to explain a particular data set
so let's say I'm I'm a young child or
zoologist and I'm in the forest and I
see an animal I've never seen before is
that animal part of an existing species
that I know or is it part of a totally
new
species and and there's two hypotheses
at this moment I don't have enough data
to decide between either of them I'm
going to conduct as a scientist
experiments well uh just going back a
little bit it means that I have a
posterior with two different models that
are equally likely or or somewhat
likely and then I'm going to um conduct
an experiment to decide whether this
animal is part of an existing or new
species which means that to do that I
need to have some notion of what would
happen if I did that like Information
Gain about the model I'm using about the
world this is like a super simple
example of like we fundamentally need
that in a for one in a biomatic agenda
of like creating agents that you know
resemble us and modeling and so forth
also from a statistical perspective of
like not
overfitting but pretty hard to do in
practice how about coming back to one of
arun's questions
um in what ways is time a special
Dimension we talk about planning through
time and and that's
intuitive from a folk psychological
perspective how does the
model handle time similarly or
differently about rgms or just in
general I mean what what what is time
how is it being treated similarly or
differently to other
dimensions um yeah good question I think
it's a very fundamental and also
physical
question um but just in terms I mean
very very simply in terms of the model
time is the only direction that we can
uh
control is the only I mean we can't
control the flow of time but we can
control the evolution through State
space as time and faults and those are
actions now uh one interesting thing
about the paper is that we not only
renormalize in space in state space but
we renormalize in time and so we have
this u in the current architecture this
one step ahead actions at each level uh
time Horizon of one it could also be two
or four or whichever you want as long as
is the same as at each
level um but yeah the point is we
renormalize both in space and time and
uh I would be I think this would be a
good question for Carl of like why is it
important to renormalize both in space
and time I don't really have a sense for
uh what that is but he probably has a
very compelling reason for for what that
is I'll give a little bit of details to
why I asked the question so there's a
very technical reason and then there's
like a wider reason the very technical
reason is to do with the overlapping
part that we talked about before and I
noticed in the paper there doesn't seem
seems to be there doesn't seem to be
overlapping
time
uh uh sort of factors you go from one
state above to generates the initial
State at the level below and then a
transition and then you do the next pair
but the pair of observations at the
level below don't overlap whereas in the
mest example you had uh there were
radial basis functions that were like
four pixels wide or whatever um but they
overlapped which I thought was really
interesting so that was the very
technical reason why I asked oh is time
separate here where the pairs don't
overlap as you're doing the
renormalization uh but I think the wider
question of why it's interesting is that
I don't really understand how you would
plan with respect to space but as you
say like with time it's it's the roll
out that's the critical dimension of you
go if I do this then in the future
something
happens but I my my brain doesn't
compute what planning would look like in
space but yeah we'll definitely ask
Carin the dot two and probably be just
as confused at the end
but that kind of makes me think of a
wave propagating out like in a game of
life situation a wave is prop
propagating out at one one click per
time step so it's moving it's a
wavefront in
SpaceTime from the surfer on the wave
they're not
moving but then renormalized over space
it's like what will happen to that time
Step at the next time step well if it's
if it the wave is going to hit it or
it's going to leave but from the waves
perspective renormalizing through
SpaceTime it's
stationary it's a stationary traveling
wave that still is treating time in a
little bit of a different way than space
but for all systems that we're studying
in time which basically are the natural
systems we can't really get away from it
but maybe there's like a hypertime
crystal view on some of these systems
that spatializes
time okay in some of our for that yeah
in some of our last uh pieces again if
if anyone has questions feel feel free
to write it okay Rex asks how has the
progression been with the Atari
challenge encouraging
results um yeah I mean really good
question I'm not sure how much I'm able
to share um just because of
confidentiality issues but but I would
say um overall it's quite
challenging uh definitely very
interesting results um many different
approaches that are being tried because
of course you could I mean you have this
rgm approach but there's many other
types of gen of models that you know you
could be exploring for solving this type
of task um the interesting deep question
is what kind of structure or structures
is sufficiently universal to be able to
express any kind of a Tar game and the
day we saw that we we actually have
learned a great deal at the moment we we
we have some leads we have some
promising results but we are still far
away from uh being able to solve all the
games with the same
structure uh so I think there's a very
interesting progress in terms of scaling
up um but yeah still still far and as
always with these um research questions
is always hard to know you know how how
long we'll need to to actually solve the
challenge
yeah maybe just think of the
game how children pick up
games and Calvin ball making up
games and what cognitive capacities
support the idea like maybe there's a
[Music]
game hanger or highlevel game
virtualizer that then can be like a
Sandbox for creating games with
arbitrary structure you know you're
going to tell me a number that ends in a
Seven and then I'm going to do this
dance it's like that's our game but
because it's a rule set within a space
within a container that's
understood and so although generalized
coordinates rgm and so
on in theory can go for infinite number
of
dimensions for any finite
system it may only be several levels of
generalization or path extraction or
just in the example of time even with
two time steps per
level at some point with time doubling
you're talking about a transition that's
longer than a
lifetime so it becomes a kind of an EXT
EST aneous inference and similarly
making it finer scale you're going to
quickly get to the state transitions of
walking at a Picos second which again
don't really matter but if there
were either automated ways or
interpretable human in the loop type
ways to say okay the SVD is looking
pretty pretty pretty uninformative
at this small scale and at this large
scale here's the bulk of the Miso
variants that we're working
with here's the information content
across these coarse
graining here's sweeping across
different windows and graining this
looks like a good a good graining
approach here's where the meat is to
chop up and that relates to the
focusing the computational resources on
where the information content
is focus the resources on where there's
information to
glean and then truncate the model's
dimensionality beyond the point of
diminishing
returns like it it almost it's it's it
goes without saying slash is hard to say
sometimes but that's an extremely
different parad Paradigm for fitting
small to very large models than coming
with a fixed number of parameters of a
large model and a fixed data set as much
as you can and then colliding the two
until you can optimally reproduce the
training
data while there is this element of
parameterizing it on training data
in principle you can just specify
generative models and generate synthetic
data we do this all the time for
different models it doesn't you don't
have to train them on anything you can
just make a thermometer in a synthetic
room and just let it
play so it's just interesting how with
these new Lego
toolkits and new compos
abilities
that can deal with data and play in that
sort of empirical test train
mode but they also lend themselves to a
lot more Dynamic
reconfiguring that I think is the main
piece we've
been wrestling with which is it gives us
more
affordances in building and modulating
these
models but every degree of freedom in
the modelers toolkit is double-edged
because it expands the combinatorics of
what is
possible possibly diminishing the
proportion of good
Solutions but maybe those good Solutions
get better and better though they're
rarer and
rarer just want to come in on a quick
point which I think you talked about the
at the very high scale nothing really
happens across you know beyond a
lifetime at the very small scale you
don't want to consider walking on Pico
seconds from a practical point of view I
guess that's going to be very limited by
your training data so for example from
on the spatial point of view it's what
does a pixel mean in your training data
and presumably you have to normalize
across all your different samples to be
a pixel means the same distance in an
image regardless potentially like or do
do you have to do some sort of uh pre
processing to mean that you're only ever
taking data from the same pictures from
the same camera at the same distance for
that to mean the same thing across the
different uh bits of your
data um or does if they are different
does your model then have to learn that
from structural point of view uh and
then going on the time one I think
that's also quite interesting maybe it's
another reason why it's different if
you're introducing videos of different
lengths so if you say okay here's some
data where in this particular video it's
10 it's 100 frames and this one it's 200
frames there's different levels of re
you're limited in uh how far up you can
go if you're just going to continually
pair and pair and pair if you've only
got 100 frames compared to 200 frames so
there could be very practical
considerations here for the number of
levels you can have and how like what
time scale you can operate on but then
also I think it's it does beg the
question
at the very top level if you've only got
like I think for p let's say for the
music example in this
paper you've if you've got a length of
music and you it breaks it down like it
was jazz music and you break it down
into like notes and bars and potentially
you could go up to a movement but you
can only go up to the maximum level like
length of your like a piece of
music that is that you're that you're
exposing in the training data you can't
go above that and that sort of like
highest level thing could only really
have like one value so you might as well
get rid of it so there's some there
might be some redundancy at the very top
there that you just sort of can always
implicitly throw
away yeah I think so I mean
when yeah um and and when we have the
current architectures I mean we always
show the the top level as having for
example one state or or two states with
transition to another two states but
then implicitly you have this um even
higher level that has one State uh and
that's static but yeah somehow he I mean
it doesn't do anything
so um but yeah there's many things um I
guess many questions and many things
that could be
explored the the other thing uh another
question that I have is so inly let's
say we're thinking okay um I need to go
to work I need to take a certain amount
of actions to go to work intuitively
when we plan in that setting there's
several actions that happen in the same
at the same level or arguably maybe not
everybody's like this
but uh it's like I need to go down I
need to you know take my car and then I
need to go up the elevator uh uh at the
workplace and so forth um if it seems
that this plan maybe happens at the same
level of of abstraction or like there's
many cases where where we plan on the
same level of of abstraction and in the
current rgm architecture we just have
one step ahead or like a fixed amount of
steps
ahead that are reproduced at each
level
so yeah I mean it you can definitely
reproduce the example that that I talked
about by by saying okay well we're going
to plan you know 10 steps ahead at each
level and then you will fit with more
complex plans but you know how can we
allow some flexibility there or is there
some flexibility that we need for for
the time Horizon at each level should
should it be different from one level to
another and so
forth yeah well it's like the the trolls
in the studio are being explored and
fleshed out because you could sweep
across different planning Horizons or
you could plan for the same amount
across Horizons like just like um it's
brought up with the when it's uh
connected to the
convolutional neural network
um it it talks about how the special
case where all of the
where the likelihood mappings are
conserved over groups one has the
discrete homologue of convolutional
neural network so if you're just trying
to make the best single filter to pass
over an image you have a
CNN whereas if you open it up to
different locations of the image having
different
filters that's the blessing in the curse
now you have that many times larger of a
state space but for problems that have
that statistical structure that would be
the way to go so that's what motivates
this meta modeling question of how would
we recognize whether we're in a
situation where single filter is better
than n number of filters like these are
where the modeling questions quickly
rise in a way because where our
inference hits the metal we know how
that's going to happen in terms of
basian graphical model and variational
free
energy it's just how to know what level
of abstraction to enter into the problem
and really what's the purpose of the
model because it's really easy to set up
a situation where the for example policy
inference is a slam dunk and it's easy
to set up situations where the policy
inference is hopeless by Design so what
is that sort
of goldilock
Zone
where if you could curate only the
expert gameplay examples and do
resemblance
modeling but if you already knew who is
expert then you already have those
traces so it's like just it it's
interesting how with a strong
floor and grounded in a really
lowlevel way to balance accuracy and
complexity we really quickly hit these
data science
questions about what the analysis is for
and what what structure the model should
be taking
on um okay in our last
minutes okay another question question
are any other benchmarks being looked at
or just what kinds of benchmarks do you
think for the open source Community
would be interesting for us to
pursue uh with
acation and um with
RG um
so with RGN um so yeah I mean there's
several things right so there could be
imitation learning
benchmarks uh I think this would be very
interesting to to go into because
arguably this isn't I mean the current
state of rgms it's an imitation learning
tool it's not really a planning Tool uh
it's also a compression
tool
um in terms
of
uh so so there's a
t um but arly if we really want to solve
a T we want to put a planner in the rgm
so we just we don't want to be a to
learn necessarily from expert data we
want to learn in a self-supervised way
and so the very things that we're
exploring there uh extensions of rgm in
in various
ways um and then and then you know I
mean there's um there's so many
benchmarks out there uh one thing that's
interesting for going to aari is
minari um and then there's all of the
robotic uh benchmarks that I think are
quite
interesting um I mean you probably know
uh many many other interesting examples
but yeah I think these are the most yeah
interesting ones at least from my
perspective it also depends on on the
feature that you're developing right so
maybe RMS are particularly good for
imitation
learning uh but if you're in multi-agent
active inference then you probably want
to look at multi-agent games or things
that require a cooperation to to solve
certain types of problems um yeah I
would say it's very much open-ended and
depending on on the strength of the
particular approach
okay what are your next uh moves I mean
how will your year proceed and what are
you what are you excited
for I'm super excited about um this
model uncertainty
thing
um this idea of how how do we do Bas in
princip of models
in a way that's fast fast enough so that
we can
plan uh to take actions that improve our
model over
time and and this is also interesting I
guess from um bridging multiple Fields
together because when we look at um for
example the work in computational
cognitive
science um by by folks like Justin B Sam
gersman they they think very much in
terms of inferring the model of the
world having a distribution of models of
the world is not something that we're
doing again at the moment and I think
this is a limitation um when you look at
other folks like yosua Benjo who are
interested in AI safety and also AI
driven scientific discovery they also
have this uncertainty about models um
and this based in inference which is uh
very important and
interesting so then
when you accept that this is uh the way
that things need to be done then there's
the question of how do you infer how do
you do the Bas inference in practice and
there and there's a wide set of tools of
um for doing approximate inference of
models it's still relatively young field
so there's lots of improvements to be
done there lots of the hardcore
statistics and machine learning very
deep questions so this is like one
direction that I think is interesting to
pursue and and then once you have that
working well and by working well I mean
you want a method that's able to infer
models very fast it doesn't need to be
super
accurate uh when you think about
humans uh we
typically only have uh you know a few
hypotheses about the call structure of
something or something the world so we
don't necessarily need to have a super
complex approximate posterior of models
also that would be very competion
complex so we want to look for uh things
that are fast and that operate
online uh and so once you have these
kind of methods for inference about
model then putting that into an agent
and having the agent learn the
noo um you know in a in a
self-supervised way uh in in its
environment and and the other challenge
for that
is uh because you're doing model
inference there's
no it's not strictly speaking it's not
model growing or pruning anymore you're
just doing model inference so your space
of models is fixed from the
outset um and so therefore if you want
developmental agents or lifelong
learning agents you want a space of
models that can pretty much explain
anything the agent would ever
encounter or you want a space a model
that is able to express anything that
the agent would need to
survive um so you don't necessarily want
something that's to incomplete but you
want something that's you know a class
of models that's pretty
expressive but it should also be
sufficiently course that you're able to
do efficient infint on it so you have
this trade-off which is very difficult
to navigate of um trying to find a class
of models that is universal in some
sense but also sufficiently course that
you can you know do things uh manageably
and I think this is where um rgms Can
potentially be very
fruitful um because they are very
expressive and they're also so I mean
they have very powerful inductive biases
this like renormalization aspect that
makes your model space a lot smaller
than it would be with other methods so
this uh yeah this is a one way forward
I'm like particularly excited
about cool yeah expert learning is kind
of the inductive side and then the
creativity and the abduction and being
able to jump to an adjacent possible
from what has been induced that's
exciting
umun and then kind of have our last uh
thoughts here uh I thought that all of
those uh directions of future research
sound really interesting uh I had a very
possibly silly question uh which is on
when we're talking about learning about
structure are we also learning about
potential new actions that an agent
could take and I think that ties in the
AI safety part quite nicely of currently
in active inference if you come up with
your own generative model as the modeler
I can say these are the actions
available to my agent it can only do
these things it has to pick one of those
things and it can't do anything else but
if we're going to learn online about
possible actions like new actions I
could take suddenly now I learned that I
have the choice to drive a car whereas
before I could only walk then suddenly
the range of impacts that I could have
my me as the agent can have on the world
massively increases and is possibly not
predicted by the modeler at the time
they're creating their agent so I think
that so yeah my question is sort of
about what type of structure do we want
to learn with these new models and does
that include actions that an agent could
take yeah um I mean really interesting
question and um so so I'll give you a
couple of of thoughts um the there is a
to Toby Sinclair Smith uh which you've
probably had had here on the show um he
yeah he he does category Theory and and
in his latest formulation of um of
structure learning acence with category
theory he talks about blankets that
change over time and so this would be
this idea of adding removing actions of
observations um so I think that's
interesting and and he would probably
have some some really cool thoughts
about that the other perspective is
let's say you fix the observation space
and the action
space
um and let's suppose that if that I as a
person exists only in a like a small
part of my head and my observations and
actions are the information that's
coming in and out of this small part of
the head now when you're a baby you
don't know that you can act on your body
right so you don't know that your foot
is you and your arm is you but you're
going to learn eventually that there is
a very precise mapping from the
information that's coming out of your
action neuron to what your arm can do
and So eventually even though your arm
is a latent State you're going to
associate moving my arm with an action
that you're taking because there is a
very precise mapping from your neuron to
what the arm does and I think this would
be um this would basically when you when
you think about it this way uh there is
maybe a lot of actions that we can lump
into the latent states of the
environment that we have direct a very
precise control over that that's the way
I'm thinking about
things yeah
that's that's the Babbling it's
interesting I'm also just thinking of
expert video of figure
skating but then there that doesn't mean
it's safe for a
non-expert or there could have been a
body position that was safely reached
but then if a different object in a
different context is so there's so many
interesting um
fundamental issues and that is the sort
of Benchmark and reprod reducibility
question is how can we compare models
with these radically different forms
possibly in the future also radically
different substrates solving these
problems in different ways such that the
ways that benchmarks are even
conceptualized in terms of like CPU or
Ram may only be a constrained way to
think about how some of these embodied
problems are solved um Lance thank you
for this and all the authors for the
work we're very excited to uh talk with
Carl and others in 58.2 during the
applied active inference Symposium so
good luck with your
Works see you next
time thank you so much thanks
everyone e